{"tossups": [{"question": "Charles E. Mitchell briefly halted this event, which was predicted by Roger Babson\u2019s namesake\u201cbreak.\u201d Richard Whitney attempted to curtail the damage caused by this event, which was studied by the Pecora Commission. The Glass-Steagall Act was passed in the wake of this event and required commercial and investment banking operations to be separated. Margin calls fueled panic on \u201cBlack Monday\u201d and\u201cBlack Tuesday\u201d during, for ten points, what inciting incident of the Great Depression?", "answer": "<b> Wall Street crash</b> of 1929 (or<b> stock market crash</b> of 1929; prompt on Black Thursday and/or Black Tuesday before mentioned; prompt on the Great Depression before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In the leadup to this war, Ansar al-Islam was defeated in the north by a CIA-supported force from the Peshmerga. Lynndie England was imprisoned for dereliction of duty during this war for mistreating POWs. Four years after his war began, a \u201csurge\u201d strategy was employed by the commander of the Multi National Force, David Petraeus. Colin Powell argued at the UN that the presence of weapons of mass destruction was enough pretext to launch, for ten points, what war that toppled Saddam Hussein?", "answer": "<b> Iraq</b> War (accept Operation<b> Iraqi Freedom</b>; accept<b> Second</b> Persian<b> Gulf</b> War, but do not prompt on \u201cGulf (War)\u201d alone)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Note: two answers required. The Seven Missions territory changed hands in a 1750 treaty between these two countries. The bull<em> Aeterni Regis</em> signified papal approval of a treaty signed between these two countries. Both of these countries\u2019 claims to the Moluccas Islands led to the 1529 Treaty of Zaragoza, a follow-up to an earlier agreement that a line 370 leagues west of the Cape Verde Islands would be used to separate New World claims. The Treaty of Tordesillas was signed by, for ten points, what two Iberian countries?", "answer": "<b> Spain</b> and<b> Portugal</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This character uses the informal insult \u201cCasse toi\u201d [cah-say TWAH] in his opening appearance before declaring himself \u201cthe best.\u201d This figure, who announces \u201cI\u2019m takin\u2019 this horse by the reins, makin\u2019Redcoats redder with bloodstains,\u201d tries to rhyme \u201canarchy\u201d with \u201cmonarchy\u201d shortly before Hercules Mulligan and John Laurens give their verses in the song \u201cMy Shot.\u201d Daveed Diggs portrayed Thomas Jefferson and this man in the original Broadway cast of<em> Hamilton</em>. For ten points, name this marquis who aided the colonies during the American Revolution.", "answer": "(Marie-Joseph Paul Yves Roch) Gilbert du<b> Motier</b>, Marquis de<b> Lafayette</b> (accept either or both underlined names) Page 1", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "This city was the site of a 1911 uprising remembered by the Yellow Flower Mound. The Whampoa Military Academy was founded in this city, which was made a treaty port under the Nanking Treaty. The Thirteen Factories were located in this city, where Hongs managed trade with Europeans. This port city on the Pearl River was connected to Hong Kong via the Kowloon-Canton Railway in 1910. For ten points, name this southern Chinese city in Guangdong.", "answer": "<b> Guangzhou</b> (or<b> Canton</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Karl Radek argued against signing this treaty, arguing that revolutions would soon occur that would render it unnecessary. This treaty, whose terms were annulled in the Treaty of Rapallo, made the Kars Oblast an Ottoman territory. Demands for \u201cpeace, land, and bread\u201d fueled one side to accept the harsh terms of this treaty, which included giving control of the Baltic States to Germany. For ten points, name this 1918 treaty that took Russia out of World War I.", "answer": "Treaty of<b> Brest</b>-Litovsk", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This leader oversaw the abolition of privy purses by passing the 26th constitutional amendment in 1971. This leader\u2019s son Sanjay advocated for a mass sterilization program that this leader implemented during a period known as the Emergency. This leader was assassinated in retaliation for launching a military assault on Amritsar\u2019s Golden Temple as part of Operation Blue Star. For ten points, name this daughter of Jawarhalal Nehru, the first female Prime Minister of India.", "answer": "<b> I</b>ndira<b> Gandhi</b> (prompt on \u201cGandhi\u201d) Page 2", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A politician from this country reportedly held up a copy of<em> The Constitution of Liberty</em> by Austrian thinker Friedrich von Hayek and stated \u201cThis is what we believe.\u201d Another economist from this country used wine from Portugal and cloth from this country to define comparative advantage in trade. A political economist from this country wrote<em> On Liberty</em> and<em> Utilitarianism</em>. For ten points, name this home country of David Ricardo and John Stuart Mill.", "answer": "<b> United Kingdom</b> of Great Britain and (Northern) Ireland (or<b> U.K.</b>; accept Great<b> Britain</b>; accept<b> England</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In a work partially named for this figure, Minerva points to a printing press near famed inventors and Liberty holds a<em> fasces</em> and wears a Phrygian cap. This figure leans on his horse at Verplanck\u2019s Point in New York in a John Trumbull work that was followed by a similar pose of this man in front of Evacuation Day proceedings. The government commissioned Constantino Brumidi to paint the<em> Apotheosis</em> of this leader for the US Capitol rotunda. For ten points, name this man whose portrait was saved by Dolley Madison during the burning of D.C. in 1814.", "answer": "George<b> Washington</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Hot deck imputation used by this agency was ruled constitutional in the case<em> Utah v. Evans</em>. Robert W. Marx helped create the TIGER system for this agency, and it also used the UNIVAC I computer. Frederick Jackson Turner developed the Frontier Thesis after this agency stopped tracking the frontier in 1890. Federal courts have blocked this agency from including a citizenship question in its upcoming forms. The U.S. Federal Statistical System includes, for ten points, what agency that, since 1790, has tabulated data about the American people every 10 years?", "answer": "U.S.<b> Census</b> Bureau", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "An Adele Berlin article about \u201c[this book] and Ancient Storytelling\u201d argues that it was meant to be a historical novella. Herodotus\u2019 description of the domineering Amestris is associated by some scholars with this book\u2019s character of Vashti, who is ousted as queen for refusing to appear at a banquet. King Ahasuerus is saved by Mordecai and the plot of Haman is thwarted in, for ten points, what book of the Old Testament, named for a queen of Persia, that depicts the origins of Purim?", "answer": "Book of<b> Esther</b> (prompt on \u201cMegillah\u201d)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "This ruler deposed his client king, Cotys I of the Bosporan kingdom, in favor of annexing the Crimean Peninsula. This emperor used a collapsible boat in an attempt to kill his mother; when that failed, he killed her with an assassin. This ruler committed suicide in 68 AD after it was clear Galba would take over. For ten points, name this adopted son of Claudius, a Roman emperor who legendarily fiddled while Rome burned.", "answer": "<b> Nero</b> Claudius Caesar Augustus Germanicus", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This ruler was declared to be the rightful king in a letter sent to Pope John XXII, the Declaration of Arbroath. This man refused to rule jointly with John Comyn and instead killed Comyn in a church. This ruler agreed to the 1326 Treaty of Corbeil with France to renew the Auld Alliance. This man became Guardian after Edward I won a July 1298 battle against William Wallace, forcing Wallace to resign. Edward lost the 1314 Battle of Bannockburn to, for ten points, what Scottish king?", "answer": "<b> Robert the Bruce</b> (or<b> Robert I</b> of Scotland; prompt on Robert)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This project\u2019s employees included Lilli Hornig, who was initially given typist orientation instructions. Maria Goeppert Mayer won a Nobel Prize for her work done with this project. Leona Libby, a grad student at the University of Chicago, helped construct an experiment</b> <b>at (+)</b> <b>Stagg Field for this project. Lise Meitner refused to work on this project, the</b> <b>subject of a 2014 book by Denise Kiernan about women brought to (*)</b> Oak Ridge, Tennessee. Chien-Shiung Wu provided troubleshooting advice to Enrico Fermi about neutron poisoning for, for ten points, what military research project, the subject of Kiernan\u2019s<em> The Girls of Atomic City</em>, that produced the first atomic bombs?", "answer": "<b> Manhattan Project</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {}, {"question": "Though this man suffered serious wounds at the</b> <b>Battle of Lundy\u2019s Lane, he recovered and led U.S. Marines in storming (+)</b> <b>Chapultepec</b> <b>castle in the Mexican-American War. This man\u2019s most famous scheme called for the (*) </b>blockade of Southern ports after the outbreak of the Civil War. For ten points, name this general known as \u201cOld Fuss and Feathers\u201d who proposed the Anaconda Plan.", "answer": "Winfield<b> Scott</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In this country, Gui Bonsiepe designed an operations room in accordance with Gestalt psychology. Stafford Beer and Fernando Flores helped implement a cybernetics program in this country. The state development company CORFO operated in this country, where</b> <b>Project (+)</b> <b>Cybersyn was implemented. In 1970, Army commander Ren\u00b4e Schneider was</b> <b>Cybersyn was implemented. In 1970, Army commander Ren\u00b4e Schneider was</b> <b>fatally shot in a failed kidnapping supported by the CIA; three years later, an (*)</b> <b>fatally shot in a failed kidnapping supported by the CIA; three years later, an (*)</b> AK-47 given by Fidel Castro was used in the suicide of this country\u2019s president. For ten points, name this country where Salvador Allende was overthrown in a coup led by Augusto Pinochet.", "answer": "<b> Chile</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A book repudiating this man\u2019s most famous achievement is marred by errors, including a claim that Giovanni de Marignolli was mentioned by name in a period document. This man\u2019s embellishments include a story in which he taught the art of building mangonels to</b> <b>the (+)</b> <b>Mongols. Fra Mauro\u2019s world map depicting Asia may have been influenced by a</b> <b>Mongols. Fra Mauro\u2019s world map depicting Asia may have been influenced by a</b> <b>map this man had. This man apparently failed to tell (*)</b> <b>map this man had. This man apparently failed to tell (*)</b> Rustichello da Pisa about chopsticks or a Great Wall in his stories of meeting Kublai Khan. For ten points, name this Venetian who traveled to China in the 13th century.", "answer": "Marco<b> Polo</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s most famous work contains a seven-year hole later filled by the</b><em><b> Hellenica</b></em><b>. This man\u2019s military experience in Corcyra led him to conclude that \u201cwar is a violent</b> <b>teacher.\u201d The argument \u201cthe strong do what they can and the weak (+)</b> <b>suffer what they</b> <b>must\u201d is posed to the diplomats of Melos in a work by this man, who recorded a speech that ends \u201cSo died these men as becomes (*)</b> Athenians.\u201d The funeral oration of Pericles is related by, for ten points, what author\u2019s<em> History of the Peloponnesian War</em>?", "answer": "<b> Thucydides</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>Supporters of one candidate in this election year cut their hair and shaved their beards in an effort to \u201cget clean for Gene\u201d McCarthy, whose 42 percent in the New Hampshire</b> <b>primary caused the (+)</b> <b>incumbent president to drop out. Abe Ribicoff spoke out against</b> <b>the \u201cGestapo tactics\u201d used against protesters at this year\u2019s (*)</b> Democratic National Convention. Hubert Humphrey gained the Democratic nomination after the assassination of Robert Kennedy in, for ten points, what year in which Lyndon Johnson did not run for re-election and Richard Nixon was elected president?", "answer": "US presidential election of<b> 1968</b> (prompt on \u201c68\u201d)  (1) <b>During an economic depression in this country, killing a cow merited a longer</b> <b>prison term than murdering a person. The Maleconazo uprising took place in this</b> <b>country, where the collapse of the USSR necessitated a (+)</b> <b>\u201cSpecial Period in a</b> <b>Time of Peace.\u201d Carlos Pr\u00b4\u0131o Socarr\u00b4as helped a future leader of this country buy a yacht called (*)</b><em> Granma</em> for a journey from Mexico to this country, where a revolution against Fulgencio Batista succeeded in 1959. For ten points, name this Caribbean country once ruled by Fidel Castro. ANSWER:<b> Cuba</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}